Eugene Malan

Bloomington, MN 55438

www.emalan.com eugene@emalan.com

ENTERPRISE JAVA SOFTWARE PROFESSIONAL

"Eugene is a great resource for the team when it comes to Java related issues.

Eugene's commitment to his work and willingness to put in the extra effort, makes him a valuable member of the BI development team.

The level of rigor that Eugene gave to building these interfaces and the supporting documentation allowed the team to more accurately test interfaces to spec.

A 10 minute conversation with Eugene often times will save two hours of analysis time."

> -excerpts from Performance Evaluations and Peer reviews.

- Experienced Software Developer with over 10 years of solid experience on large corporate projects. 6 years using Enterprise Java technologies on large web based commercial applications.
- Sun certified Java Developer with expert-level knowledge of Java and the Java JDK.
- Knowledgeable and up to date on current technologies and development philosophies.
- In-depth knowledge of, and ability to setup, an efficient Java-centric development environment.
- Hard working, committed team player that can fit in and be productive quickly.

SKILL SUMMARY

Languages: Java, SQL, shell scripts, PowerBuilder

Java Frameworks and Technologies: Struts, WebWork/XWork, EJB,

Servlets/JSP

Java Libraries: JDK, Jakarta Commons, Junit, Cactus, Mock Objects,

Pluto, Log4J, Junit

Java-centric XML: XML, SOAP, Xerces, JDOM, DOM4J, Web Services

Web Technologies: HTML, Tags, Javascript, Ajax techniques IDE's & Servers: Eclipse, IntelliJ, Weblogic, JBoss, Tomcat Operating Systems: Linux, Unix, Mac OX, Windows

Database: Sybase, Oracle, MS SQL, MySQL

Java skills

- Expert level knowledge of Java and the Java JDK as well as experience and ability to efficiently use many of the most useful and common open-source Java libraries.
- Practical experience with Java development using the Extreme Programming methodology.
- Struts, WebWork/XWork

Linux Administration

Linux administration skills that include the following: general Linux installation and setup, Network setup, DNS server, LDAP server, Apache HTTP, CVS repository, Email SMTP(Spam filtering, procmail delivery), Samba network, NFS, NIS. I have a running SuSE Linux service that provides most of these services.

Database skills

I have strong Relation Database skills and have been involved in all aspects of database development from design to data manipulation. I have excellent SQL skills including extensive stored procedure experience and a good understanding of performance issues on relational databases.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Application Developer, Gelco Information Network, Inc

08/2005 - 12/2006

IT Environment: Java-centric, Web Application, Struts, EJB, Weblogic, Oracle, CVS, CruiseControl, Eclipse, Extreme Programming methodology

- Developed the new Syndicated Data module of the application on my own. Coded the Persistent Layer as well as the UI. I received recognition as being quick to learn and get up to speed at my new job.
- Gained valuable experience using EJB's. Coded Entity Beans and Session Beans. Made use
 of Interfaces and DTO's to keep the EJB layer encapsulated and create easy to use objects
 for the UI to use.
- Successfully completed the Syndicated Data Load that involved a number of tricky technical problems. The Load parsed large XML data files, batched the data and saved it to the database. Technologies used included, Dom XML parser, JMS queues, XBeans and EJB.
- Matured as a developer by being influenced by the Extreme Programming methodology.
 Started making extensive use of Junit Tests and refactoring to produce better quality code.
- Responsible for maintaining the CruiseControl build.

Software Engineer, Achieve Healthcare Technologies

06/2001 - 07/2005

IT Environment: Java-centric, Web application, XWork/WebWork, JDBC, Stored Procedures, MS-SQL, CVS, CruiseControl, IntelliJ

- Managed the Reporting Architecture project adding new functionality, refactored the existing code.
- Sole Developer resource for SSP/PSG, involving gathering requirements, new functionality
 and extensive refactoring of existing code to be more OO. Played an instrumental part in
 choosing to move to a web framework so that the same validation and persistence code
 could be used for back-end interfaces as well as normal user input.
- Became part of the architecture team and was tasked with delivering the first XWork/WebWork functionality. Setting up standards and example usages for XML validation, tags, wizard functionality, i18n
- Transferred to BI development team to bring Enterprise Java knowledge to this team.
 Extensive code rewrite using XWork/WebWork. Mentoring of developers on using framework and OO design principles and design patterns.
- Java reporting interfaces to MSSQL Reporting Server using SOAP and a HTML proxy.
- Integrated Portal application into main application using Pluto code and successfully demoed to Company.
- Developed portlets for use in the Portal including weather portlet making use of the NOAA's SOAP API.

Information Technology Consultant, RCM Technologies, Inc

03/1998 - 03/2001

- Successfully completed 2 contracts with clients. Both contracts were extended, the Wells Fargo one for 2 years.
- Developed my Java skills while part of a team that was preparing for an internal Java project at RCMT. Attended courses on Java technologies and benefited from knowledge transfer from RCMT's Java expert

Wells Fargo IT - IT Environment: PowerBuilder 6, Win 95, NT, Sybase 11, UNIX, Novell City of St. Paul - IT Environment: PowerBuilder 5 on Windows 95, Oracle

IT Consultant, Lewis Stores, South Africa

05/1997 - 03/1998

- Developed and implemented a Delivery Tracking application in PowerBuilder v.4 on a Sybase database. Wrote user documentation and trained users
- Involved in the maintenance of a Stock System. Included developing and implementing enhancements to the system
- Designed and developed the client side of a "Stock Ordering" application in PowerBuilder v.5. The screens made use of the new tab objects and the application was designed to be distributed
- Investigated the migration of all existing systems from PowerBuilder v.4 to v.5. A full migration of the Stock system was performed and tested. Various migration problems were highlighted and fixed

Senior Programmer, Saftainer, South Africa

1995 - 1997

- I was transferred to Saftainer IS department from a position as Assistant Financial manager and left Saftainer as a development coordinator in charge of a financial module developed in PowerBuilder v.4 on a Sybase database
- The work included major enhancements to the system and included the whole spectrum of Analysis, Design, Development, Testing and Implementation
- I had to do a lot of work under pressure to allow the system to function while performance issues where threatening the project as a whole. I did extensive work to increase the performance of the program, including taking some processing off line and into batch jobs that ran overnight

Various Accounting, South Africa

1990 - 1994

Standard Bank, South Africa

1982 - 1985

EDUCATION

University of South Africa, Pretoria, South Africa

BACHELOR OF COMMERCE (Information Systems/Economics)

1995

SUN CERTIFIED PROGRAMMER FOR THE JAVA 2 PLATFORM

2001

HIGHLIGHTS OF CONTINUING PROFESSIONAL EDUCATION:

No Fluff Just Stuff - Twin Cities Software Symposium

March 2006

- Introduction to Hibernate
- Enterprise AOP with AspectJ

- Advanced Hibernate

- Ajax Architecture
- Java/J2EE Architecture @ Work: EJB Spring Intro
- 3 vs Spring and Hibernate
- Spring Dependency Injection